Script and Production Research Materials for Dr. Ehrlich's Magic Bullet Biomed.0007
UCLA Library Special Collections
Script and production research materials for Dr. Ehrlich's Magic Bullet
1881-1940
UCLA Library Special Collections
Belt, Elmer, 1893-1980
Biomed.0007
1 unknown (1 volume, 34 cm.)
The collection includes the script, photographs, and research materials gathered to support production of the 1940 Warner Bros. motion picture, Dr. Ehrlich's magic bullet, which focused on Paul Ehrlich's work to develop effective chemical cures for diphtheria and syphilis. A bound oversize album contains many illustrations to guide studio set designers, props, art and costume departments, etc. Articles, many of which have been excerpted and translated from the original German, include biographies, some of Ehrlich's publications, and commentaries on his syphilis treatment.
Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Acquisition Information
The collection was a gift from Dr. Elmer Belt to the UCLA Biomedical Library.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9966356043606533
Scope and Content
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1. The Motion Picture., 1939-1940. 1 album and 6 folders
Series 2. The Man., 1911-1939. 13 folders
Series 3. The Science., 1881-1937. 22 folders
Syphilis - drug therapy; Motion pictures - production and direction -- Archival resources; Ehrlich, Paul, 1854-1915; Diphtheria -- drug therapy; Arsphenamine.; Belt, Elmer, 1893-1980
- The Motion Picture., 1939-1940; Series 1.; 1 albums
  - Production album., 11.5 x 14 x 3", buckram and leather bound
    Scope and Contents note
    materials gathered by the studio's Research Department, led by Herman Lissauer, to support the movie production; most of the content is pictorial, appropriate for Ehrlich's time; some of the sections are named: the cast, Koch's laboratories, Ehrlich's laboratories and study, hospitals and laboratories, general props, medical props, cafes, courtroom, chemical factory, home interiors, makeup stills, production stills, etc.; also included is a listing of sources consulted for Ehrlich's biography and his work, and references for art and costume research, plus a selected list of his publications
    General note
    the volume in its present form was probably bound on the order of Dr. Elmer Belt
  - Dr. Ehrlich's Magic Bullet script., 13 October 1939; 140 p., 8.75 x 11.5", buckram and leather bound (Box 1, Folder 1)
    typed script, with "10/13/39 FINAL" on the first page; interspersed throughout are script pages typed on blue paper, with various later dates indicated
  - Program for Press preview showing of Dr. Ehrlich's Magic Bullet., 01 February 1940; 6 x 8.5", 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    fold-out pamphlet providing: Cast of Characters; Credits; The Story; Production Notes
    the screening took place at the Warner Brothers Hollywood Theatre
  - "Apropos of "The Magic Bulletin", by E.L. Tuchy., 1940; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    an editorial from "Minnesota Medicine", 23:433-434
    Dr. Tuchy gives a favorable review of the movie and urges attendance
  - Paul Ehrlich's study in Frankfurt., 8 x 10" photographs (Box 1, Folder 4)
    four photographs of the study: 1-2. taken at the same time, one with Dr. Ehrlich, the other with Ehrlich and his secretary, Martha Marquardt; 3. photo taken some later time, with an older Dr. Ehrlich; 4. pencil sketch for the movie set design, based on the original photographs
  - Edward G. Robinson as Paul Ehrlich., 8x10" photographs (Box 1, Folder 5)
    eight composite photos: six showing Robinson in different costumes and depicting different ages, each with an insert of the original Ehrlich photograph upon which the pose is based; two show multiple shots, again pairing Ehrlich with the comparable Robinson impersonation
  - Portraits of Paul Ehrlich. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    two portraits at different ages, one sitting, one standing
- The Man., 1911-1939; Series 2.; 13 folders
  Arrangement note
  roughly chronological
  - "Paul Ehrlich, the Man and the Scientist; recollections of the years 1902-1915, with an introduction by Dr. Richard Koch", by Martha Marquardt., 1924; 79 p. (79 sheets); paper cover (Box 1, Folder 7)
    title page dedication reads: "Paul Ehrlich, on the occasion of his 70th birthday, March 14, 1924"; Martha Marquardt was Ehrlich's secretary for 13 years, and her goal was not to write "...of the great scholar, but of the simple, unassuming man."
    typed translation of the German original which was published by Deutsche Verlags-Anstalt Stuttgart, 1924; no indication of the translator; "Belt Collection" is typed on the paper cover
  - Materials furnished by the Ehrlich Family., 5 p. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    typed translated excerpts from three Ehrlich letters: 1. to Prof. Salomonsen, Kopenhagen, Nov. 27, 1899; 2. to Dr. Christian Herter, Jul. 10, 1909; 3. to Prof. Christian Herter, New York, Feb. 24, 1910
  - Notes and excerpts from Hedwig Ehrlich's diary., 17 October 1939; 8 p. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    92 separate translated events, most between two to six typed lines long; very few items are dated
  - "Personal impressions of Dr. Paul Ehrlich and his work", by B. C. Corbus., 1911; 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    photocopy of article in American Journal of Clinical Medicine, v. 18, 1911
    Dr. Corbus, a Chicago physician, visited Ehrlich in Frankfurt to learn about Salvarsan's use in syphilis
  - "Paul Ehrlich's last illness and death"., 31 August 1915 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    typed translation, photocopy of the original newspaper article, and reprint of the "Letter from Frankfurt a.M." published in Münchener medizinische Wochenschrift
  - "Paul Ehrlich - in memoriam", by Carl Ludwig Schleich., undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    two slightly different typed translations and a photocopy of the original article
    p. 1409-1419, headed "Rundschau"; no other identification
  - "Recollections of Paul Ehrlich", by Martha Schiff., 11 p. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    typed rough translation of an article printed in Deutsche Revue
  - "Paul Ehrlich: persönliche Erinnerungen an ihn von einem seiner Freunde"., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    photocopy from unidentified printed source, signed H. [perhaps Dr. Christian Herter ?]; the short biographical description includes portraits of Ehrlich's mother, father, and Ehrlich as young man
  - "Paul Ehrlich, 1854-1915", by G.H.F. Nuttall., 1924; 7 p. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    biographical note, with portrait and transcription of an Ehrlich letter to Nuttall, published in Parasitology, 16(2): 224-229, 1924
  - "Paul Ehrlich, 1854-1915", by Robert Muir., 11 p. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    photocopy of a review of Ehrlich's life and work from Journal of Pathology and Bacteriology, 20(2): 350-360
  - "Paul Ehrlich", by Alfred Lichtwitz., 1915; 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    photocopy of obituary from the Deutsche Monatsschrift für Zahnheilkunde, 33: 433-436
  - "Paul Ehrlich"., 28 August 1915; 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    photocopy of an editorial and a death notice from the Journal of the American Medical Association, 65(9): 803-804, 814
  - Encyclopedia entries for Ehrlich. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    two short biographies from unidentified German sources
- The Science., 1881-1937; Series 3.; 22 folders
  - "On methylene blue and its utilization in clinical-bacterioscopical work", by P. Ehrlich., 1881; 7 p. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    typed translation of an article from the Zeitung für klinische Medizin, v. 2.
  - "The organism's need for oxygen: a study in the analysis of dyes", by P. Ehrlich., 1885; 17 p. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    typed translation headed "Gist", possibly excerpted from the 167 p. volume Das Sauerstoff-Bedürfniss des Organismus. Eine farbenanalytische Studie; Berlin, 1885
  - "The reaction of methylene blue on living nerve substance", by P. Ehrlich., 28 January 1886; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    typed translation of one paragraph excerpted from an article in Deutsche medizinische Wochenschrift.
  - Three articles by Max Gruber on Ehrlich's antibodies., 1901-1902; 9 p., 2 p., 14 p. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    1. photocopy of "Zur Theorie der Antikörper. I. Ueber die Antitoxin-Immunität", by Max Gruber (in two parts), from the Münchener medizinische Wochenschrift, 48(46-47): 1827-1830, 1880-1884; 2. photocopy of "Ehrlich's theory of haematic antidotes", in The Medical Press, Dec. 25: 682-683; 3. photocopies of presentation and discussions at several meetings of the Gesellschaft der Aerzte in Wien, published in Wiener klinische Rundschau, v.15-16(no.47-51, 2):800-801, 910-912, 931-932, 952, 969-1970, 25-26
  - "Paul Ehrlich discusses his syphilis specific"., 1910; 9 p. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    photographs of typed translation of an article from the Frankfurter Zeitung lent by Walter Bertheim
  - Speech by Dr. Ehrlich presented at the 82nd meeting of the "Deutsche Naturforscher und Ärzte", Königsberg., 20 September 1910; 17 p. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    typed translation, taken from the publication of the Proceedings in "Deutsche medizinische Wochenschrift", v.36, n.41, 13 Oct 1910
  - "The treatment of syphilis with the Ehrlich specific 606"., 13 October 1910 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    photocopy of 10 pages of Proceedings of the 82nd meeting of "Deutsche Naturforscher und Ärzte", Königsberg, 20 Sep. 1910, under the above title; typed translations of three speeches (all with notation "gist"): 1) by Dr. Ehrlich (3 p. - full translation of same speech in Box 1, Folder 26); 2) by Dr. A. Neisser (2 p.); 3) by Dr. Alt (6 p.)
  - The Salvarsan trial at Frankfurt., 07 June 1914-10 June 1914 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    nine typed translations from German newspapers Frankfurt, Berlin, Munich) regarding the libel trial of Karl Wassmann, who, among other charges, accused the doctors of the City Hospital, including Ehrlich, of using prostitutes as experimental guinea pigs to undergo toxic Salvarsan treatments
  - "Le Professeur Ehrlich a l'Hôpital Broca"., 07 February 1914 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    photocopy of account in Presse Médicale (no. 11) of remarks by Paris doctors and Ehrlich's comments regarding treatment of syphilis with Salvarsan
  - Excerpts from the Festschrift in honor of Ehrlich's 60th birthday., 1914; 5 p. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    "Paul Ehrlich; eine Darstellung seines wissenschaftlichen Wirkens", by H. Apolant et al. Jena, G. Fischer. 1. Biographical Introduction, by A. von Weinberg: a rough translation of the last two paragraphs of the original thirteen-page chapter; 2. Analytical studies of dyes, by L. Michaelis: translation of the section devoted to methylene blue; 3. The side-chain theory, by A. von Wassermann, a rough translation
  - "The Salvarsan question", by Dr. Gennerich, 13 March 1914; 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    typed translation of the gist of an article in Naturwissenschaften, in the journal issue dedicated to Ehrlich in honor of his 60th birthday
  - "L'ouvre de Paul Ehrlich", par Roux et Metchnikoff., 16 March 1914 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    photocopy of an article in French, printed in the Berliner klinische Wochenschrift, no. 11
  - "Excellenz Geheimrat Dr. Paul Ehrlich"., circa 1914; 5 p. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    photocopy of text and portrait from an unidentifiable source, possibly a book or review on the role of Jews in science and medicine
  - "Salvarsan fatalities and their causes, with reference to the harm done by Salvarsan", by Artur Schmitt., 16 June 1914; 5 p. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    typed translated gist of excerpts from an article published in "Münchener medizinische Wochenschrift"; also two translated paragraphs quoted from the Salvarsan trial in the same newspaper issue, p. 1373-1374
  - "Paul Ehrlich", by August von Wassermann., 9 and 16 September 1915 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    photocopy of the original articles from Deutsche medizinische Wochenschrift (nos. 37-38, p. 1103-1106, 1135-1136) and typed partial translations
    Wassermann provided both a review of Ehrlich's life and a review of his scientific accomplishments
  - "Paul Ehrlich", by Albert Neisser., 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    photocopy of an article from Archiv für Dermatologie und Syphilis, 121:556-578
    Dr. Neisser provides a lengthy review of Ehrlich's scientific work, plus a list of biographical highlights and a three-page bibliography of Ehrlich's fundamental publications
  - "Eine sterbende Krankheit: vom Aufstieg und Niedergang der Syphilis", by Gerhard Venzmer. Leipzig: Montana-Verlag., 1929; 40 p. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    a partial translation, especially of pages 61-89, under the title "A vanishing disease"
    the text covers a short history of syphilis in the world, a short biography of Ehrlich, and a more detailed description of his work leading to Salvarsan and the subsequent decline in the prevalence of syphilis
  - "Salvarsan -- twenty years after", by Richard Koch., 23 September 1930; 14 p. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    typed translation of an article from the "Frankfurter Zeitung
  - "Men who conquered death: the fate of famous researchers in their battle with microbes. Preparation 606 -- Salvarsan.", 27 August 1927; 11 p. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    typed translation of an article in "Die Berliner Nachtausgabe", section 3
  - The work of the State Institute for Experimental Therapy and of the George Speyer House, Frankfurt am Main., 1924; 44 typed pages (Box 2, Folder 9)
    photographs of a typed translation of the German original, published by Gustav Fischer, Jena
    originally published as no. 16 of the series: "Arbeiten aus dem Staatsinstitut für Experimentelle Therapie und dem Georg Speyer-Hause zu Frankfurt a. M."
  - "History of the side-chain theory of Paul Ehrlich", by Bruno Heymann., 1 July 1928; 9 p. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    typed translation of excerpts from Klinische Wochenschrift
  - "Paul Ehrlich: a man of genius, and an inspiration to humanitarians", by Herman Goodman., 1937 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    photocopy of article published in The Urologic and Cutaneous Review, v. 41: 630-633.
    Dr. Goodman reviews Ehrlich's scientific accomplishments